#### Contact

1-231-680-0608 (Home) mhotwagner@gmail.com

www.michaelhotwagner.com www.linkedin.com/in/mhotwagner

### Top Skills

Python

Django

**JavaScript** 

**AWS** 

**PostgreSQL** 

Docker

### Languages

English (Native or Bilingual)
Spanish (Professional Working)

# Michael Hotwagner

Senior Software Engineer @ Hired | Full Stack Developer Rosendale, New York, United States

## Summary

Full stack software engineer with over a decade of experience designing, developing, and implementing functional and elegant solutions to interesting problems. Proven ability to work with clients (or as the client, as it were) from design through development and implementation to efficiently deliver an excellent product.

# Experience

Hired

Senior Software Engineer June 2020 - July 2024 (4 years 2 months)

New York, United States

Hired Assessments is a hiring-adjacent platform for evaluating candidates through custom assessments, including real-time coding questions across numerous languages. The Hired Assessments backend stacks include Django, Flask, Postgres, Celery, Redis, nginx, and docker (for code evaluation), all deployed on AWS infrastructure including ElasticBeanstalk, RDS, Elasticache, and AWS Lambda.

As the Senior Software Engineer for Backend and Infrastructure, I have...

Developed, built, and maintained backend business logic in django + postgres, supporting the react, vue, and vanillajs frontend apps through apis in graphql and rest.

Maintained and built out the real-time code evaluation api app in flask + docker, and supported the connection to the backend django app through a graphql api.

Maintained and updated support for existing languages in the real-time code evaluation app, and developed and built out support for new languages. (Languages I support include javascript, python2, python3, ruby, java, clojure, swift, c++, rust and bash, among others.)

Designed, built, and deployed into production a replacement for the docker-based real-time code evaluation runners using AWS Lambda.

Maintained all aspects CI deployment pipeline with github + travisci + elasticbeanstalk, and maintained all aspects of deployed AWS infrastructure, primarily on ElasticBeanstalk, RDS, and Lambda.

WeWork

Lead Internationalization Engineer March 2018 - February 2020 (2 years)

Greater New York City Area

Developed and managed the internationalization infrastructure for a diverse ecosystem of applications across web and mobile, for both internal clients and external end-users.

Worked closely with localization team and engineering stakeholders to build and manage tools for easy and automated integration with the internationalization process and the localization workflow.

Worked with third-party vendors to integrate and support tools to supplement on-site localization.

Designed, built, and deployed a in-house internationalization management system to integrate with platform-agnostic client apps and automate the internationalization process and localization workflow.

Voxy

Full Stack Software Engineer September 2015 - February 2018 (2 years 6 months)

Greater New York City Area

Voxy is a world class English language learning app, driven by real, research based pedagogy. My responsibilities with Voxy included:

- Contribute to multi-tenant, configurable English language learning app deployed in the AWS ecosystem, serving 50k+ active monthly users in both B2B and B2C contexts.

- Architect, develop, deploy, and maintain all components of the app, including AWS infrastructure, Python/Django backend and API, Postgres, Mongo, and Redshift stores, data pipeline for reporting and analytics, learner-user clients on web (Vue.js, legacy Backbone) and native iOs and Android, and adminuser clients on web.
- Collaborate with product team to plan and timeline feature development, and to deliver those features using agile and TDD methodologies in iterative sprints.

Fluent City

4 years 7 months

Full Stack Developer October 2013 - September 2015 (2 years)

Brooklyn, New York

Fluent City is a cultural organization offering fun, social language classes across 10 ten languages in New York, Washington, D.C., Philadelphia and Boston. As developer and technology director, my work entailed:

- Collaborate with external design team on design and wire-framing.
- Organize and implement development sprints, tracking against larger project timelines.
- Prototype new products for a/b testing and iterate on them.
- Continuously plan, develop and maintain Fluent City's customer-facing website.
- Develop and maintain integration between internal database of record and Salesforce for customer/lead information.
- Actively contribute to all aspects of Fluent City, including driving process, business goals, and organizational development.

Core stack included:

Python, Django, PSQL, HTML, CSS/SCSS, Javascript, Heroku, Git, PHP, MySQL, Wordpress

Spanish Teacher

March 2011 - January 2015 (3 years 11 months)

Greater New York City Area

Fluent City is a cultural organization offering fun, social language classes across 10 ten languages in New York, Washington, D.C., Philadelphia and Boston. In my time with Fluent City, I've...

- Instructed adults in beginning and intermediate level Spanish.
- Collaborated with Academic Director to plan curriculum.
- Generated class textbook and supplementary in-class materials.

#### Protocol

**Technology Lead** 

August 2011 - October 2013 (2 years 3 months)

Protocol is an innovated gift company located in NYC, designing and promoting unique products, as well as running a number of side-operations. While I was with Protocol, I...

- Liaised with graphic design, development and product owners to develop company websites, including associated ChariTotes project.
- Managed internal and external web-based and mobile application projects (incl. iOS, Android and Blackberry platforms).
- Built and maintained two separate but connected Magento-based e-commerce programs to handle all online transactions.
- Maintained all office technology and software.

iD Tech — Camps, Academies & Online Instructor
June 2011 - August 2011 (3 months)

Cmb Realty Inc
Temporary Assistant to the President
January 2011 - May 2011 (5 months)

New York State Democratic Committee Canvassing Team Leader August 2010 - November 2010 (4 months)

Lake of the Woods & Greenwoods Family of Camps Camp Counselor June 2010 - August 2010 (3 months)

## Education

Central Michigan University

Bachelor of Arts (BA), Political Science · (2006 - 2010)